Finding Aid for James E. Scripps Papers 1858-1940
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
James E. Scripps Papers 1858-1940
Scripps, James E. (James Edmund), 1835-1906.
Detroit, Michigan, newspaper publisher. Papers of Scripps and of the James E. Scripps Trust established to ensure that control of Scripps's Evening News Association would remain with his immediate family. Series in the collection include: biographical material, notably unpublished biography and personal diaries, 1858-1868 and 1872-1881; business records of various Scripps newspapers and publishing companies; George H. Scripps probate records; and James E. Scripps trust records.
86994 AC Aa 2
9 linear feet
2 oversize volumes
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The papers were donated by the descendants of James E. Scripps, through Peter B. Clark (donor no. 7301 ) in March 1986.
The collection is open for research.
Microfilm copy of Scripps' diaries, 1858-1881, available.
James Edmund Scripps, Detroit newspaper publisher, was born March 19, 1835 in England, to James Mogg Scripps, a bookbinder, and his second wife, Ellen Mary (Sandus) Scripps. In 1844, the family came to the United States and settled on a farm near Rushville, Illinois. There James worked on the family farm and attended the district school.
In 1857, Scripps left Rushville for Chicago. There he attended Digby V. Bell Commercial School and received his diploma in twelve weeks. Vowing to be successful in business, Scripps's first job was in a lumberyard for a salary of $400 a year. When this establishment failed in September 1857, Scripps secured a position as a reporter for the Democratic Press, published by his cousin, John Locke Scripps. Financial troubles at the paper resulted in employment cutbacks, and J.E. Scripps lost his position. He then worked temporarily directing Canadian sheep pelts to Chicago markets. In 1859, after a brief return to Rushville, Scripps became commercial editor of the Detroit Daily Advertiser. Two years later, Scripps became part owner of this paper, and, in 1862, when the Advertiser merged with the Detroit Tribune, he became business manager and later managing editor. In the same year, Scripps married Harriet Josephine Messinger.
Throughout his first decade in the newspaper business, Scripps contemplated marketing a small, inexpensive, but well-written newspaper containing a minimum of advertising. On August 23, 1873, Scripps founded just such a paper, The Evening News. Although the paper originally lost money, it began to pay for itself after six months in operation. By 1875, all losses had been replenished and a profit of $6,000 was recorded. On August 23, 18T6, The Evening News was incorporated as the Evening News Association. James E. Scripps held the majority interest. Other incorporators included his brother George, his half-brother Edward Wyllis Scripps, his sister Ellen Browning Scripps and a cousin, John S. Sweeney.
The Evening News continued to grow, and by 1877, the paper employed 640 persons. Five years later the paper reported a circulation figure exceeded only by ten other papers in the country. Foreign cable service, shared with the New York Post, the Chicago News, and a few other papers, began in The Evening News on May 5, 1885.
The success of The Evening News encouraged James, George, and Edward to start newspapers in Cleveland, St. Louis, and Cincinnati. Those papers controlled by members of the Scripps family became known as the Scripps' League. In 1877, James E. Scripps made an agreement with his two brothers over control of the papers, and spent two years abroad for health reasons. After his return in 1889, growing disagreements over managerial, financial, and editorial concerns led James E. Scripps to withdraw The Evening News. By this time, George B. Booth, Scripps's son-in-law and eventual successor, had joined the staff of the Evening News Association.
As the success of the Evening News Association continued, James E. Scripps considered reducing the price of The Evening News to one cent. To test the existence of a market for a paper of this price, Scripps created his own competition by starting the Detroit Times, which sold for one cent, in August 1890. The success of this paper revealed a hospitable market. Accordingly, Scripps lowered the price of The Evening News to one cent on October 1, 1892. The Detroit Times merged into The Evening News in the sane year.
In October 1893, the Sunday News and Sunday Tribune were combined under the name the Sunday News-Tribune, later renamed the Detroit News-Tribune. At this point, the Evening News Association was printing The Evening News, the Detroit Tribune, and the Sunday News-Tribune.
After the death of George H. Scripps in 1900, James E. Scripps and Edward W. Scripps struggled in bitter litigation for control of the Evening News Association. The issue was to determine the residence of George H. Scripps, who left a will, which named William A. Scripps and Edward W. Scripps as executors, and was admitted to probate in Cleveland. James E. Scripps claimed that Detroit had been the home of his brother George, and that, therefore, the will should have been offered for probate there. James also wished to have the will declared invalid in order to prevent the transfer of the shares of George H. Scripps in the Evening News Association to Edward Whyllis Scripps. If such a transfer occurred, Edward would have been the second largest stockholder and might have eventually gained a controlling interest. The result of this conflict was that James E. Scripps relinquished all ties with the Scripps' enterprises in exchange for complete control of the Evening News Association.
Shortly thereafter, James E. Scripps established a thirty-year trust to ensure that control of the Evening News Association remained with his immediate family. Upon his death in 1906, the trust was administered by William E. Scripps, his son, and George G. Booth and Edgar B. Whitcomb, his sons-in-law.
This collection contains both the personal papers of James E. Scripps and the records of the thirty-year trust he created shortly before his death in 1906. This collection is divided into four series: Biographical Materials, Business Records, George H. Scripps Probate Records, and James E. Scripps Trust Records. Although the bulk of this collection concerns the running of the Evening News Association, the most captivating items are those which pertain to the life of James E. Scripps. The records of the Evening News Association, the James E. Scripps Corporation, and the James E. Scripps Trust, with related litigation materials, attest to the complexity of this Detroit newspaper operation.
Subjects:
American newspapers--Michigan--Detroit.; Detroit (Mich.); Evening News Association.; Journalists--Michigan--Detroit.; Scripps, George H., d. 1900.; Scripps, James E. (James Edmund), 1835-1906.; Scripps family.; Travelers.; Voyages and travels.
Genre/Form:
Diaries.
- Biographical/Personal Material
  Biographical Materials contains a lengthy biography, completed in 1943, by Cyril Arthur Player, which is an invaluable source of details on the life of James E. Scripps. Also in this series are two folders of autobiographical material, including notes made by Scripps as early as 1857 and 1861. Of interest are the annual diaries kept by Scripps from 1858 to 1881. These speak of travels in the United States and Europe, family, and the newspaper business. Two additional journals, recording travels to Europe in 1881 and 1889, are equally fascinating.
  - "Story of James E. Scripps" (unpublished manuscript) by Cyril Arthur Player, 3 volumes (Box 1)
  - Autobiographical materials, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Correspondence 1858-1859 (Box 1)
  - Diaries, 1858-1881
    (microfilm copy available)
    - 1858-1868, 12 volumes (Box 1)
    - 1872-1881, 11 volumes (Box 1)
  - European Journal 1881, 1 volumes (Box 2)
  - European Journal 1887, 2 volumes (Box 2)
  - "The Heraldic Achievement of the Ancient Family of Scripps", 1 volumes (Box 2)
- Business Records
  Business Records includes a personal day-book and ledger, a statement book for the St. Louis Chronicle, and a record book of the U.S. Press Bureau, a group created to manage the foreign advertising of the Detroit News, Cleveland Press, Cincinnati Post, and St. Louis Chronicle. Following this are the Articles of Incorporation for the Scripps Publishing Co., correspondence concerning the Scripps-McRae League, and record books for the Evening News Association, the Detroit Publishers Association, and the Bay City Times.
  - James E. Scripps day book 1873-1906, 1 volumes (Box 2)
  - James E. Scripps ledger book 1873-1906, 1 volumes (Box 2)
  - U.S. Press Bureau, record book 1888-1894, 1 volumes (Box 2)
  - St. Louis Chronicle statement book, 1893-1902, 1 volumes (Box 2)
  - Scripps-McRae League 1898 (Box 2)
  - Evening News Association, ledger 1898-1904 (Box 2)
  - Scripps Publishing Co.-Articles of Incorporation 1899 (Box 2)
  - Detroit Publishers Association, record book 1902 (Box 2)
  - Bay City Times journal, 1903-1914 (Box 2)
  - Bay City Times ledger, 1903-1914 (Box 2)
- George H. Scripps Probate Records
  The next series - George H. Scripps Probate Records - includes records of the probate settlement in Cuyahoga County in Ohio followed by testimony and related papers. Four scrapbooks containing newspaper articles documenting the progress of the litigation between James E. Scripps and Edward W. Scripps over the will of George B. Scripps and the future of the Evening News Association follow. These scrapbooks also contain articles on a trial occurring in March 1907, in which John S. Sweeney attempted to claim a controlling interest in the Evening News Association, based on an agreement concerning stock transfer signed twenty years earlier.
  - Probate Records 1900-1902 (Box 3)
  - Testimony, 6 folders (Box 3)
  - Related Papers (Box 3)
  - Scrapbooks re: Suit over George H. Scripps probate 1903
    - Detroit Free Press (Box 3)
    - Detroit Journal (Box 3)
    - Detroit Evening News (Box 3)
    - Detroit Times (Box 3)
- Trust Records Of James E. Scripps
  - General Trust Records
    Beginning the Trust Records Of James E. Scripps series are "General Trust Records," such as a copy of the original will and trust agreement, and reports, minutes, and annual statements.
    - Will and Trustee Agreement 1906 (Box 3)
    - Letter of Trusteeship 1912 (Box 3)
    - Distribution of Copies of Will of James E. Scripps, 1 volumes (Box 3)
    - Report of President to Stockholders 1907-1911 (Box 3)
    - Minutes of Trustee Meetings 1924-1927 (Box 3)
    - Trustees Annual Report
      - 1911-1921 (Box 3)
      - 1922-1931 (Box 3)
    - Annual Statement of Account
      - 1911-1918 (Box 3)
      - 1919-1926 (Box 3)
    - Correspondence 1906-1924 A-Z, 17 folders (Box 4)
  - James E. Scripps Corporation Annual Statements
    The James E. Scripps Corporation, created by James E. Scripps shortly before his death, was organized with a capital stock of $700,000.00. George G. Booth, Edgar B. Whitcomb, and William E. Scripps bought three shares in the company and James E. Scripps bought the remaining shares for $699,700.00. The corporation, which bought all of the real estate holdings of James E. Scripps, excluding his home, for $699,700.00, became part of the living trust. This subseries includes annual statements for the corporation.
    - 1916-1920 (Box 4)
    - 1921-1923 (Box 4)
    - 1924-1925 (Box 4)
    - 1926-1927 (Box 4)
    - 1928-1929 (Box 4)
    - 1930-1931 (Box 4)
    - 1932-1933 (Box 4)
    - 1934-1935 (Box 4)
    - 1936-1937 (Box 4)
    - 1938-1940 (Box 4)
  - Tax Materials
    The Tax Materials subseries relates to the trust. Aside from annual income tax reports from 1917 to 1940, the bulk of the papers here relate to litigation which occurred between 1925 and 1928. The issue disputed was whether the beneficiaries or the trustees should pay taxes on income, when the distribution of this income among the beneficiaries is discretionary with the Trustees. The records located here include correspondence, legal records, and materials documenting transactions following the litigation.
    - Income Tax Reports
      - 1917-1922 (Box 4)
      - 1923 (Box 4)
      - 1924-1926 (Box 4)
      - 1927-1928 (Box 4)
      - 1929-1930 (Box 4)
      - 1931-1933 (Box 4)
      - 1934-1935 (Box 4)
      - 1936-1937 (Box 4)
      - 1938-1940 (Box 4)
    - Tax Cases
      - Information Return 1917-1926, 1936 (Box 4)
      - Income Tax-Report of Revenue Agent 1918-1922 (Box 4)
      - Tax Data 1918-1924 (Box 4)
      - Report Covering Audit of Receipts and Disbursements 1906-1924 (Box 4)
      - Appeal to Tax Board and Suit in District Court of the U.S. 1924 (Box 4)
      - U.S. Board of Tax Appeals-Petitioner's Brief (Box 5)
      - U.S. Board of Tax Appeals-Proceedings 1924 (Box 5)
      - Decision of Board of Tax Appeals 1925 (Box 5)
      - Plea Amended 1927 (Box 5)
      - Over Assessments 1918-1922 (Box 5)
      - Loans from Beneficiaries to Trustees 1924 (Box 5)
      - Settlement of Tax Cases 1918-1924 (Box 5)
      - Correspondence 1921-1928 (Box 5)
      - Beneficiaries-Advice on Taxable Income 1924-1938 (Box 5)
      - Trustee and Estate Statements 1915-1936 (Box 5)
      - Dividend Notices 1924-1933 (Box 5)
      - Investments 1924, 1938, 1939 (Box 5)
      - Personal Property Tax 1924-1936 (Box 5)
      - Miscellaneous Bills, Statements, Letters, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Clark Suit
    In the "Clark Suit", resolved in 1928, the plaintiffs, Rex B. Clark and Grace S. Scripps, asked that stock of the Evening News Association be distributed among the children of James E. Scripps immediately. In defense, the Trustees held that such stock should not be distributed until the expiration of the trust in 1936. In a decision handed down in Circuit Court in June 1928, the validity of the trust was upheld. Included here are correspondence between the Clarks and the Trustees, testimony, court records and expense statements.
    - Correspondence
      - June 1910-May 1913 (Box 5)
      - June 1914-December 1923 (Box 5)
      - January 1924-April 1924 (Box 5)
      - May-August, 1924 (Box 5)
      - September-December, 1924 (Box 5)
      - 1925-1926 (Box 5)
      - 1927-1929 (Box 5)
      - 1930-1933 (Box 5)
      - 1934-1936 (Box 5)
      - 1937 (Box 5)
    - Testimony, 4 folders (Box 5)
    - Exhibits (Box 5)
    - Evidence and Miscellaneous (Box 5)
    - Related Information (Box 5)
    - Brief for Defendants, 1 volumes (Box 6)
    - Brief for Plaintiffs, 1 volumes (Box 6)
    - Record, 1 volumes (Box 6)
    - Opinion of Court (Box 6)
    - Expenses and Ending Correspondence (Box 6)
    - Newspaper Clippings (Box 6)
  - Assignments
    - Deed-Grace S. Clark to Rex B. Clark 1919, 1928 (Box 6)
    - Rex B. Clark to Farmers and Merchants National Bank of Los Angeles 1928 (Box 6)
    - Rex B. Clark, Grace S. Clark, to Detroit Security Company 1929 (Box 6)
    - Ellen S. Booth to Cranbrook Foundation 1930 (Box 6)
    - William E. Scripps to William J. Scripps and Nina D. Scripps 1933 (Box 6)
    - Anna S. Whitcomb to Edgar B. Whitcomb 1933 (Box 6)
    - William S. Clark, Rex Scripps Clark, Ellen Clark Revelle to Detroit Trust Company 1934 (Box 6)
    - Rex B. Clark to David Faris, cancellation 1936 (Box 6)
  - Trust Closing
    - Agreement between Evening News Association and Trust 1936 (Box 6)
    - Bill for Judicial Settlement of Trustees Account 1935-1936 (Box 6)
    - Dissolution of the Trustee of James E. Scripps 1936 (Box 6)
    - Voting Trust for Stock of Evening News Association 1936 (Box 6)
    - Trust Closing Receipts 1936-1940 (Box 6)
    - Tax Payments 1936-1939 (Box 6)
    - Beneficiaries Agreement to Form Committee February 2, 1938 (Box 6)
    - Distribution Receipts February, 1938 (Box 6)
    - Final Statement April 27, 1940 (Box 6)
    - Trust Closing Material, 8 folders (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous Bound Volumes
    - Trial Balance 1891-1893 (Volume 1)
    - Trustee Record Book 1906-1928 (Box 6)
    - Trustee Minute Book 1906-1940 (Box 6)
    - Check Registers 1906-1940, 4 volumes (Box 7)
    - Estate Journal 1906-1937 (Box 7)
    - Estate Ledger 1906-1937 (Box 7)
    - Trustee Journal 1906-1936 (Box 7)
    - Trustee Ledger 1906-1936 (Box 7)
    - Trustee Journal 1936-1940 (Box 7)
    - Trustee Ledger 1936-1940 (Box 7)
    - Trustees Statements- Evening Times, Bay City Times, James E. Scripps Corporation, May 1906-December 1915 (Box 7)
    - Trustees Statements (Evening News Association Bay City Times), January 1909-May 1918 (Volume 2)
    - Financial Statements 1924-1940 (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous Records
    - Vouchers (Box 8)
    - Canceled Checks (Box 8)
    - Check Book 1924-1928 (Box 8)
    - Bank Statements (Box 9)